Inventory to the Records of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities 1965-1984 RG 21.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities
1965-1984
RG 21.1
New York University Archives
7.0 linear feet (12 boxes, 25 tapes)
In 1965 the New York State Board of Regents awarded New York State University the funds to create an Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities as part of a state-wide attempt to improve higher learning. Several chairs, five of which were designated by the State Legislature as the Albert Schweitzer Chair and five as the Albert Einstein Chair in Science, were intended to attract the world's most renowned scholars to New York State's higher educational community. The inventory to the Records of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities chronicles the records of this position from 1965-1984. The recipients of the additional chairs were City University of New York, Cornell University, the University of Rochester, State University of New York at Stony Brook and Fordham University; however, information about chairs at other institutions are not recorded in this collection.
Cantor, Norman F.
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Additional Information
List of participants in events sponsored by Aileen Ward:
David Kaelstone
Galway Kinnell
Louise Gluck
W.S. Merwin
William Meredith
Richard Howard
Richard P. McCormack
Robert E. Elliot
Wing-tsit Chan
Elizabeth Badinter
Harry Levin
Faun Brody
Quentin Bell
Diana Josselson
Richard Dyer-Bennet
Christopher Richs
Vincent Buckley
David Malouf
Les Murray
Shirley Hazzard
Dennis Donoghue
Derek Walcott
Paul Zweig
Kofi Awooner
Shatis Haviaris
Louis Simpson
Gregory Orr
Mark Strand
Shirley Williams
George Kelly
Saul Touster
Frederich Karl
Nicholas Wahl
Morton Cohen
Richard Sennett
Dustin Griffin
Frederick Morgan
Elizabeth Spires
Barbara Howes
Yehuda Amichai
David Ignatow
Philip Schultz
Walter J. Ong
Denis Johnson
Ruth Stone
Alice Fulton
Lawrence Joseph
Gary Soto
Joseph Brodsky
Adrienne Rich
Marvin Bell
Hillis Miller
Alfred Kazin
J. Nicanor Parra
Richard Rorty
Michael Scammell
Joan Peyser
Steven Stowe
George Perle
Estelle Leontief
Eileen Simpson
John Mayher
Gordon Praddl
Anthony Low
M.L. Rosenthal
Daniel Javitch
Lucien Stryk
Charles Wright
List of Participants in Conor Cruise O'Brien's Lecture Program (an asterisk indicates that the person is represented in this collection either by a scholarly paper or a tape of their lecture):
I.F. Stone
Grattan Freyer
Thompson Bradley
Jonathan Mirsky
William Garret
Leonard Boudin
Gidon Gottlieb
Julian Mayfield*
Noam Chomsky*
Peter Nettl
Eric Gently
David Erdman*
Edward Thompson*
Stuart Hampshire*
L. Zanderer*
Paul Neuberg*
George Steiner
David Caute
John Arden
George Quasha*
Thomas Hart Wilkins*
Max Gordon*
Gabriel Kolko*
Alger Hiss*
Charles P. Kelly*
Arrangement
Arrangement
Program Files
Conor Cruise O'Brien's Manuscripts
Public Lectures
Student Papers
Julian Mayfield Manuscripts
Lecture Series
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists primarily of records generated during the term of Professor Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1965 to 1969. The collection also contains a few of the annual reports written by Professors Ellison and Ward. These are located in the file "Report on the Schweitzer Chair" (Box 3, folder 1).
The records include correspondence, manuscripts, news clippings, student papers (both doctoral and undergraduate), and copies of some public lectures and tape recordings. Papers presented by fellow scholars were removed from the Series I: Program Files and organized as Series III: Public Lectures.
History of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities
The Albert Schweitzer Chair covers the disciplines of comparative literature and the history of ideas. Professors who have held this position have traditionally emphasized through their scholarship and teaching an emphasis on the relevance of the humanities to present-day concerns and the nature and quality of interracial awareness.
At New York University a faculty committee was formed to select the first Albert Schweitzer Professor. The committee chose Conor Cruise O'Brien, who was announced as the inaugural Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities on June 2, 1965. Professor O'Brien held the chair from 1965 to 1969. Following O'Brien's term, Ralph Ellison held the chair from 1971 to 1979. Professor Aileen Ward held the position from 1979-1990.
Conor Cruise O'Brien was formerly the United Nations Representative in Kantanga, Africa, and also served as Vice-Chancellor of the University of Ghana. His published works include Power and Consciousness, (co-editor); United Nations: Sacred Drama; "Introduction to Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France"; and numerous articles in The New York Review of Books, The New York Times Book Review, and The Listener. While he occupied the Albert Schweitzer Chair, he organized and participated in the annual Schweitzer Public Lecture Series, taught both graduate and undergraduate courses annually, and lectured throughout the country.
The funding for the Albert Schweitzer Chair also allowed for visiting scholars and writers to be brought to New York University. Professor O'Brien built a strong interdisciplinary program in the humanities that offered four or five courses per semester on topics such as "Art and Politics," "The Black Writer in America," "Contemporary Writing in Africa," and "Revolution and Literature."
While Professor O'Brien was at New York University he was responsible for bringing numerous scholars to lecture, read, or teach. A list of participants in the program during O'Brien's term follows the box and folder listings. In 1969 O'Brien left the Schweitzer Chair to take an elected seat in the Irish Parliament.
Successive chair holders brought their own special talents and interests to the Schweitzer Program. Ralph Ellison, chair holder from 1971-1979, is primarily a writer of fiction and criticism. His special interest is modern American writing, including literature, poetry, linguistics and politics. Besides his National Book Award-winning novel, The Invisible Man, he has written essays, short stories, articles, book reviews, syndicated columns and novels. While he was at New York University, under the auspices of the Schweitzer Chair, he developed an educational program for both the University community and the public, which included public lectures, symposia, discussions, seminars, graduate and undergraduate interdisciplinary courses and lectures by distinguished visitors. His first course at New York University, entitled "The American Vernacular as Symbolic Action," focused on the role played by the American vernacular language and style in shaping American culture and society. In the early 1970s the Chair sponsored a series of lectures for a national audience on "Law and Morality," which was widely televised. Professor Ellison brought many poets to New York University for readings and conferences, and in 1977 he organized a panel discussion with eminent Yugoslavian scholars. Professor Ellison served as a consultant to students in creative writing, doctoral students, and served on oral examination committees. He taught courses in the English Department as well as undergraduate and graduate interdisciplinary courses and was actively involved in University and community-related activities.
Some of the other courses offered by the Schweitzer Program during Ellison's term were "American Fiction and American Democracy" (taught by Anatole Broyard, and "Writers who Reshaped the American Experience After World War II" (taught by Professor Ellison). For a synopsis of Professor Ellison's activities see his summary, titled "Schweitzer Program in the Humanities," April 23, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1).
Professor Aileen Ward was the chair holder of the Albert Schweitzer Program from 1979 to 1990. A widely published and distinguished scholar, she authored several books and many articles. Areas of interest included English romantic literature and poetic theory; literature and mythology; literature and psychology; and literary biography. In the early 1980s the Schweitzer Program combined resources with the Poetics Institute (M.L. Rosenthal, founder) to provide special events open to the public. A list of those who have participated in events organized by Professor Ward in the early 1980s is included as an appendix following the box and folder listings.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The records of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities were transferred to the University Archives on June 23, 1980, by Norman Cantor, Dean of the Faculty of Arts and & Science.
Burton, John W., (John Wear), 1915-; Cantor, Norman; Chomsky, Noam; Ellison, Ralph; Erdman, David V.; Gordon, Max; Hampshire, Stuart; Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; Hiss, Alger; Kelly, Charles P.; Kolko, Gabriel; Marcuse, Herbert, 1898-1979; Mayfield, Julian, 1928 -; Mirsky, Jonathan; Neuberg, Paul; O'Brien, Conor Cruise, 1917-2008; Quasha, George; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Thompson, Edward; Ward, Aileen; Wilkins, Thomas Hart; Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities.; American literature |x African American Authors |x Study and Teaching; annual reports.; Education |x Humanities; Manuscripts (document genre).; New York State Regents Einstein and Schweitzer Chairs.; New York University |v Curricula |x History.; New York University |x Administration |x History.; New York University |x Faculty |x History.; New York University |x Graduate Students |v Periodicals.; New York University |x History |x Addresses, essays, lectures.; New York University, Dept. of Literature |x History.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; Records (documents).; videotapes.
- Series I: Program Files
  Scope and Contents
  Includes Professor O'Brien's files, 1965-1975, and material from later chair holders. This series contains a wide range of materials that pertain both to events and courses under the auspices of the Schweitzer Chair. Series I is particularly broad in scope due partly to the various functions of the Chair and partly to the depth of Professor O'Brien's interests. He shaped courses and lecture series to reflect his broad interests in politics, society, literature, and the humanities. Professor O'Brien's original organization remains with only a few alterations.
  - Visiting Professors I, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    bar code: 3 1142 04225709 0
  - Visiting Professors II, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Visiting Professors III, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Visiting Professors IV, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speaking Invitations Accepted I, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speaking InvitationsAccepted II, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Speaking Invitations Accepted III, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225710 8
  - Speaking Invitations Accepted IV, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Speaking Invitations Accepted V, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Speaking Invitations Not Accepted, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Undergraduate Exam Papers, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Condition of Jewish Belief, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mayfield Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reports on the Schweitzer Program, 1969-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225711 6
  - United Nations Seminar, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Schweitzer Confidential Matters, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - One Fifth Ave., 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Graduate Asst. and Temp. Office Help, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Schweitzer Program--Ph.D Students, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Conor Cruise O'Brien: Requests for references, jobs, interviews, etc., 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ralph Ellison, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bradley Thompson, "Disenchantment or Default" (see Series III., "Power and Consciousness"), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Schweitzer Program - student affairs, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notes for Undergraduate Students, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225712 4
  - Jonathan Mirsky, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Schweitzer Program Courses I, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Schweitzer Program CoursesII, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Schweitzer Program Courses: evening discussions I, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Schweitzer Program Courses: evening discussions II, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Schweitzer Program: Public Lectures I, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Schweitzer Program: Public Lectures II, 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Martin Luther King Institute, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Committee on "Workshop" (Black experience), 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225713 2
  - Conor Cruise O'Brien's Invitations to accept visiting Professorships, 1965-1966, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Special Invitations (Clubs), 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Fan" Letters, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Schweitzer Program Reading Lists, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Literature and Society" Lecture Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Paul Neuberg's Public Lecture (see Public Lectures, box 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Donald Lowe, "Dream of Chinese Communism", undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Manuscripts of a book on political alignments by six authors: Kenneth Kaunda, J.W. Burton, R. Sidhanta, M. Caldwell, Margaret Legum, Lucy Mair, L. Mates, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Contemporary African Writing, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Wilfred Flemming of the University of Leicester, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence/Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Student Evaluations, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Cornell's Humanities Program, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series II: Conor Cruise O'Brien's Manuscripts
  Boxes 6 and 7 contain only those manuscripts written by Conor Cruise O'Brien. These consist of two plays, two books, plus various articles and reviews. This series includes only a small portion of O'Brien's work to date.
  - "Murderous Angels" (a political play), undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225714 0
  - United Nations as Sacred Drama: Typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - United Nations as Sacred Drama: Mimeograph copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - United Nations as Sacred Drama: Handwritten copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - United Nations as Sacred Drama: Typescript and typed carbon sections of the manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - United Nations as Sacred Drama: Notebook of handwritten notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Solome and the Wild Man" or "The Quiet Man of Galalean", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225715 7
  - Albert Camus and "The Embers of Easter 1916-1966", undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Politics in West Africa;" "Christmas Books--The Last of the Highest?;" "Autonomy and Academic Freedom in Britain and Africa;" "Address to the UN;" "Nknumah--The Man I knew;" "A Negatiator on Negotiation", undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "On Yeats;" "Black Revolutionary;" "Churchill and Macmillan;" "Universities: British, Indian, African;" "A Study in the Ecology of Higher Education;" "Struggles for Africa;" "Partisan Review Questionnaire", undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Politics and Drama as Politics;" "The Writer and the Power Structure;" "Albert Schweitzer and Contemporary Africa;" "The Function and Many Roles of the Critic", undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "The Church of the People;" "Communists and Anti-Communists;" "A People Condemned;" "Beware of Melancholy;" "Burke Annotation;" "Morality of Scholarship;" "Satirical Pastoral;" "Anaylsis as Symptoms;" "Princeton Colloquim;" "Marx and History", undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "The Calculus of Pain, of Peace, and Prestige;" "The Intellectuals and McCarthy;" "A Combined Operation: The End of Ideology Debate;" "Accessories to the Fact: The Warren Commission, Authorities and the Report;" "King Herod Explains;" "Epilogue: Illusions and Realities of Non-Alignment", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Art is Man's Nature: Burke, Yeats and Conservative Imagination;" "The United Nations and World Social Revolution;" "Edmund Burke;" "Tribe Nation State;" "Ireland at the United Nations", undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Intellectuals, Public Opinion and International Relations", undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    General Note
  - "Politics and Yeats;" "Burke and Marx;" "Soldiers and Politics;" "At Home in Hell;" "Where Orange is White;" "Politics and Morality of Scholarship", undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Order, Justice and Revolution;" "Racial Conflict--Peaceful Resolution;" "After Manila;" "Modern Language Association--Address;" "The United States, The United Nations and Vietnam;" "Address to English Speaking Union in Support of Senator McCarthy for President;" "The UN as a Political Institution;" "The UN in Real Life;" "African Unity;" "The Future of African Democracy;" "African Perspectives", undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series III: Public Lectures
  This series contains copies of relatively few of the lectures given under the auspices of the Schweitzer program since 1965. These lectures include the Power and Consciousness Seminar; The Prince 1969; United Nations Seminar; and Miscellaneous (this does not reflect the complete set of lectures within each series). Most of the United Nations Seminar lectures were tape recorded (on 8-track reel to reel) and are housed in the University Archives Audiovisual Collection.
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): Power and Consciousness--introduction, Conor Cruise O'Brien, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225716 5
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): (Untitled), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Power and the Intellectual," Peter Nettl, 1967 December 6 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Objectivity and Liberal Scholarship," Noam Chomsky, 1968 March 13 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): (Copy--folder 4), 1968 March 13 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Politics and the Morality of Scholarship," Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1968 March 13 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Government and University in America," Gabriel Kolko, 1968 February 14 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Disenchantment or Default," Edward Thompson, 1968 March 20 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): (copy--folder 8), 1968 March 20 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Coleridge as Editorial Writer," David Erdman, 1968 March 6 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Imagination and Politics," Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1968 March 6 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): (Copy--folder 7), 1968 March 6 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Politics as Drama as Politics," Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1968 February 28 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): "Self-Consciousness and Society," Stuart Hampshire, 1968 April 3 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Power and Consciousness Seminar (1968): (Untitled), 1968 April 3 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Prince (1969): "Nicolo and the Prince in the White House" (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225717 3
  - Prince (1969): "What Exhortation," Conor Cruise O'Brien (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - United Nations Seminar: "Vietnam, The United States and The United Nations," Max Gordon, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - United Nations Seminar: "The United States and the United Nations," Gabriel Kolko, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - United Nations Seminar: "United Nations and United States," Alger Hiss, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - United Nations Seminar: "United States' Position on the Veto in the United Nations," Charles P. Kelly, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous: "D.H. Lawrence: Dionysian Cosmology,", undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: "The Agrarians," Thomas Hart Wilkins, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous: "The Politics of Apocalypse," George Quasha, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous: "On T.E. Hulme, T.S. Eliot and Ezra Pound," L. Zanderer, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous: "The Exultation of the Irrational", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: "Nietzsche in a World View", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: "Paris Commune", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: "Dezso Szabo and Agrarian Fascism," Paul Neuberg, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Student Papers
  Student papers have been divided into two parts: doctoral proposals and undergraduate papers. Few of the proposals are dated but they all fall within the period of the late 1960s to early 1970s. Undergraduate papers are arranged only by the professor for whom they were written.
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): Molotsi, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225718 1
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): Broyard, undated (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): O'Brien, undated (Box 10, Folder 4-10)
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): Ralph Ellison, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-10)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225719 9
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): Ralph Ellison, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225720 7
- Series V: Julian Mayfield Manuscripts
  The collectionof Mayfield manuscripts includes an early draft of his play "417" and his book The Meek Shall Not Inherit the Earth (Box 12). Mayfield's essay "Nicolo and the Prince in the White House" is located within the Public Lecture Series, and his correspondence while teaching at NYU may be found in the Program Files (Box 2, folder 7).
  - "417" (Drama), undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "The Meek Shall Not Inherit the Earth" (memoir), undated (Box 12, Folder 5-8)
- Series VI: Lecture Series Recordings
  The series contains 25 recordings, primarily of the United Nations Seminar for March and April, 1969. Alger Hiss and Gabriel Kolko discuss the United Nations and U.S. foreign policy. Among the participants are Herbert Marcuse and Conor Cruise O'Brien.
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 March 5 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225721 5
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 March 6 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 March 12 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 March 19 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 March 26 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Dated Reels: (2 Reels), 1969 April 23 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Titled Reels: Gabriel Kolko (1 reel), 1968 February 13 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Titled Reels: Conor Cruise O'Brien (1 reel), 1968 April 10 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Titled Reels: Herbert Marcuse at NYU (3 reels), undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Titled Reels: U.S. and UN Seminar, Alger Hiss, 2 lectures (2 reels), undated (Box 13, Folder 10)